pressdemocrat.com 2019-04-20

# PRESS DEMOCRAT PRIVACY POLICY

                              PRESS DEMOCRAT PRIVACY POLICY
Effective Date: July 31, 2018.
Through this Privacy Policy we provide you with important information about our privacy
practices. This Privacy Policy applies when you interact with our website and online services
and mobile applications (the “Sites”), as well as with respect to our collection and processing of
your information for our newspaper publication offline (altogether the “Services”).
For users in the European Economic Area (“EEA”) or Switzerland, please see the section below
titled Users in the EEA and Switzerland for additional provisions applicable to your use of the
Services.
This Privacy Policy explains:
        What information we gather about you;
        How we use and protect the information we gather about you;
        The types of information we may share with others and under what circumstances;
        The choices you have about the collection, use, and sharing of your information;
        Along with other administrative details like how to update your information with us.
WHEN THIS PRIVACY POLICY APPLIES:
Sites that are governed by this Policy will include a link to this Policy. This Policy applies also
when you interact with us through social media and other websites or online services. Third
party sites that are linked from our Sites are governed by their own privacy policies. When you
interact with us through social media sites, the social media platforms’ privacy policy will apply
to their collection of information. Please review the privacy policies of those websites and online
services to understand their privacy practices. With respect to our print publication, this policy
applies to our collection of your information for purposes of providing you with our Services and
communications related to or promotion of those Services.
Changes to this Policy: We will amend this Privacy Policy from time to time, and when we do,
we will post any changes to our Website. The changes will become effective when they are
posted to this page. Please check the date at the top of this policy for reference. Registered
users will be notified via email of any significant or material changes made to the way we use
your information. Your continued use of our Sites and Services following the posting of any
changes means you accept those changes.
INFORMATION WE COLLECT FROM OR ABOUT YOU
Below we describe the different types of information we collect from you at different points of
engagement with us.
Information You Give Us: Some parts of our Sites allow you to enter contact information and
other information about you. We collect and store any information you enter on our Sites,
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

including your name, mailing address, ZIP Code, phone number, email address, or other
demographic information. This information may be collected during the registration process on
our Sites and may be linked to an account number so that we can associate your preferences
online and through our Services to your account.
Information Collected Automatically: As you interact with our Sites certain information is
collected about you and your use of our Sites automatically. This information includes device
information such as computer and network connection information, your IP address and device
identifiers, your operating system and browser type; and usage information, such as your page
views, traffic that brought you to our Sites and what pages you visited after our Sites, URLs that
referred you to our Sites; and advertising data. We also collect transaction history on our Sites
and web logs (which are aggregated and used to analyze usage of our Sites), websites you
click on within emails that we send you or through pages you visit on our Sites.
Much of this information is collected and stored through your web browser or device, and using
cookies, web beacons, mobile and advertising identifiers and similar tracking technologies.
Most web browsers can usually be modified to disable or reject cookies. You may take steps to
stop the automatic use and acceptance of web trackers, but understand that if you delete your
cookies or decline cookies through your web browser, than you will not be able to access
certain areas of our Sites. For more information about Online Tracking and Advertising see
section below. For more detailed information about our use of cookies, please review our
Cookie Policy.
Information Collected from Social Media: If you log onto our Sites through a social media
platform, such as Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, and others, we and the social media service
may share certain information about you and your activities. Your interaction with social media
typically allows the social media platform to collect some information about you through cookies
they place on your device and other tracking mechanisms. In some cases, the social media
platform may recognize you through its cookies even when you do not interact with their
application. Please visit the respective privacy policies of third party social media platforms to
better understand their data collection practices and controls they make available to you.
Location Information: We log IP (Internet Protocol) addresses, and the location of your
computer on the Internet, for systems administration, troubleshooting, and for the purpose of
geotargeting our own advertisements. We use the IP address log in an aggregate fashion to
track access to our Sites. Additionally, when you interact with our Sites, we may collect
information about your location and your device. Some of this information may be general, such
as the state or city associated with your zip code, while some of this information may be more
precise, such as information associated with your mobile device. Location information allows us
to provide location-based services, and to tailor promotions to your locality. Most mobile devices
allow you to control or disable the use of precise location services in the device’s settings menu.
Other Information We May Collect: Special Offers and Events are held from time to time in the
form of contests, sweepstakes, through surveys and market research we conduct. In such
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

cases, we collect information voluntarily from you. Each special offer or event will be governed
by its own privacy terms. We will notify you if we plan to share your information with third
parties, except for in circumstances where the information is shared in the aggregate and
cannot be attributed to a particular person or response. You can always decline to share your
information by not participating in these special events or offers.
HOW WE USE INFORMATION WE COLLECT FROM OR ABOUT YOU
We may use information you give us or we collect about you to:
        Communicate with you in response to your inquiries, to fulfill your requests, or to provide
         you with offers and information about our Services or services of our affiliates and
         partners. With respect to your account with us, we may connect with you about news
         stories, features to which you may have access, surveys about our Services, and other
         important information like legal notices.
        To optimize, improve, and maintain our Sites including research and analytics regarding
         use of the Sites, identifiers that will allow us to remember you when you leave and return
         to our Sites.
        To provide and improve our products and services, both online and offline, to better
         understand and serve our users. We do so by collecting interest-based behavior
         information.
        To provide and manage the Services you request by processing your transactions at
         your request, authenticating your identity as our customer, sending you subscription
         material, electronic newsletters, and other features.
        Deliver interest-based advertising on our Sites as well as other websites and
         applications. We may use your information to deliver targeted advertisements, and offers
         or promotions tailored to you, on behalf of ourselves and other advertisers both as part
         of our Services and on other websites and mediums.
        Detect, investigate, and prevent activities that may violate our policies or be illegal or
         fraudulent. When we believe it is necessary, we will protect, enforce, and defend our
         legal rights, privacy, safety or property, or that of others. We comply with all applicable
         laws.
We may combine information collected on our Sites about you with: (1) information we obtain
from our business records, (2) information provided by third parties, (3) information collected
from your browser or device; or (4) other usage information collected on our Sites not specific to
any one individual.
We may use information collected from or about you to create aggregated or de-identified data
that does not identify you. Once the data is properly de-identified and aggregated we may share
it with third parties for their purposes.
INTERNET-BASED ADVERTISING
The Sites use the information we collect about you, such as behavioral, demographic and
preference information to provide you with advertising and offers that are more pertinent to you.
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

We partner with third party advertising companies to provide advertisements on our Sites, as
well as on other websites and applications about our products and services that may be of
interest to you.
Some of our Sites may also include advertisements or promotion content for unaffiliated
products and services. All of this means users see advertising that is most likely to interest
them, and advertisers send their messages to people who are most likely to be receptive,
improving both the viewer’s experience and the effectiveness of the advertisements.
The advertisements you see may be based on information collected through cookies, web
beacons and other tracking technologies from our Sites and on other third-party websites you
visit and mobile applications you use that participate in our advertising networks.
      Our Cookies: We may place a PressDemocrat.com cookie on your computer with a
         unique anonymous number to ensure that your browser does not see the same ad over
         and over again, to sequence ads in a series and to measure the number of unique
         visitors that have viewed a particular advertisement or visited a particular Web page.
      Others’ Cookies: Third parties may use persistent identifiers to track your Internet usage
         across other websites and mobile applications in their networks beyond the Sites. We do
         not share information that personally identifies you with unaffiliated third parties for their
         own uses. But third parties, with sufficient data from other sources, may be able to
         identify you. The information we receive from online advertising trackers allows us to
         generally inform advertisers about the nature of our subscriber base.
You can learn more about advertising serving companies and the options available to limit their
collection and use of your information by visiting the websites for the Network Advertising
Initiative and the Digital Advertising Alliance, and the webpages for Facebook’s ad preferences
tool and privacy policy. Similarly, you can learn about your options to opt-out of mobile app
tracking by certain advertising networks through your device settings and by resetting the
advertiser ID on your Apple or Android device. For more information about how to change these
settings go to:
      Apple: http://support.apple.com/kb/HT4228
      Android: http://www.google.com/policies/technologies/ads/
      Windows: http://choice.microsoft.com/en-US/opt-out
Please note that opting-out of advertising networks services does not mean that you will not
receive advertising while using our Sites or on other websites, nor will it prevent the receipt of
interest-based advertising from third parties that do not participate in these programs. It will,
however, exclude you from interest-based advertising conducted through participating networks,
as provided by their policies and choice mechanisms. If you delete your cookies, you may also
delete your opt-out preferences.
We use other websites analytics services, such as those provided by Google, Inc., to help us
administer and constantly improve the quality of our Sites. Google Analytics uses cookies or
other tracking technologies to help us analyze how users interact with and use the Sites, and
provide us with services related to our Sites’ activity and usage. Google Analytics may collect
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

information such as your IP address, time of visit, whether you are a return visitor, and any
referring website. That information will be transmitted to and stored by Google and will be
subject to Google’s privacy policies. To learn more about Google’s partner services and to learn
how to opt out of tracking of analytics by Google, click here.
Your browser or device may include “Do Not Track” functionality. At this time, Press Democrat
does not respond to browser “Do Not Track” signals.
OUR EMAIL POLICIES AND YOUR OPT-OUT OPTIONS
From time to time, we may provide subscribers with information and offers about other products
and services, including subscriptions and other premium products and services. If you do not
wish to receive emails about such offers, you may opt-out. Our email policy is the following:
     Newsletters: We offer email newsletters. If you no longer wish to receive a specific
        newsletter, follow the “unsubscribe” instructions located near the bottom of each
        newsletter.
     Promotional Emails: We periodically send emails with promotions about services we
        offer and services offered by our partners. We will not share, sell, rent, swap or authorize
        any third party to use your email address without your permission. From time to time, the
        Sites and Services may obtain email addresses from third party sources to be used for
        promotional emails. You can always opt-out of messages you do not want to receive. If
        you feel you have received an email from us in error, please contact
        info@pressdemocrat.com. If you would like to opt-out of receiving email promotions,
        please opt-out by clicking on the opt-out link at the bottom of the email you received.
     Account and Service-Related Email: Periodically we will send you emails related to your
        account with us that include information about order confirmations, renewal/expiration
        notices, notices of credit-card problems, other transactional emails and notifications
        about major changes to the Site and/or to our Privacy Policy. If you have registered for
        online discussions or other services, you may receive emails specific to your
        participation in those activities as well.
     Survey Emails: If you have not opted out, we may send you an email inviting you to
        participate in user surveys, asking for feedback on our Sites and existing or prospective
        products and services, as well as information to better understand our users. User
        surveys greatly help us to improve our Services, and any information we obtain in such
        surveys will not be shared with third parties, except in a de-identified or aggregate form.
     Emails Communications with You: If you send us emails, you should be aware that
        information disclosed in emails may not be secure or encrypted and thus may be
        available to others. We suggest that you exercise caution when deciding to disclose any
        confidential or sensitive information in emails. We will use your email address to respond
        directly to your questions or comments.
     Email This Article Feature: Our readers may use this feature to send links to articles to
        others through email. The email address(es) that you supply to this service will only be
        used to send the requested article.
     EEA and Switzerland Residents: We will only send you marketing emails if we have
        your prior consent to do so, or if you are an existing customer and our message relates
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

        to products or services that are similar to those previously sold to you, and in such cases
        you will still be given the opportunity to opt-out of further marketing emails of that nature.
HOW WE SHARE INFORMATION WE COLLECT FROM OR ABOUT YOU
If you have registered to our Sites, we will not sell, rent, swap or authorize any third party to use
your email address or any information that personally identifies you without your permission. We
do, however, share information about our audience in a de-identified or aggregate form.
The Sites may publish summaries of statistical information regarding the Sites’ visitors for
promotional purposes and as a representative audience for advertisers. These summaries will
provide broad insight at to the activities of our visitors and customers without identifying any
specific individual.
The following provides information about the entities with which we may share your information,
or the circumstances under which we may share information:
Service Providers: We contract with other companies to provide services on our behalf,
including credit-card and billing processing, shipping, email distribution, online message
processing, analytics or promotions management. We provide these companies only with the
information they need to perform their services. These service providers are restricted from
using this data in any way other than to provide us services, and they may not share or resell
this data.
We must disclose your opt-out information to third parties so they can suppress your name from
future solicitations, in accordance with applicable laws.
Other Parties as Required by Law or as Necessary to Protect Our Users, Employees,
Property, and Services: We may occasionally release information that personally identifies you
as required by law, for example, to comply with a court order or subpoena. We may disclose
information that personally identifies you if we are required to do so by law or we in good faith
believe that such action is necessary to (1) comply with the law or with legal process; (2) protect
and defend our rights and property; (3) protect against misuse or unauthorized use of our Web
sites; or (4) protect the personal safety or property of our users, our employees, or the public
(among other things, this means that if you provide false information or attempt to pose as
someone else, information about you may be disclosed as part of any investigation into your
actions).
Other Parties in Connection with a Corporate Transaction: We reserve the right to transfer
any information we have about you in connection with, or during negotiations of, any merger
acquisition, sale of assets or any line of business, change in ownership control, or financing
transaction. We cannot promise that an acquiring party or the merged entity will have the same
privacy practices as described in this Privacy Policy.
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

Otherwise with Your Consent or at Your Direction: We may share information about you with
third parties when you consent or direct us to such sharing. We may also share information with
third parties in an aggregate form that does not identify any users.
For Users in the EEA and Switzerland: Please see our Cookies Policy that provides a list of
partners that provide certain features or functionality on the Services, including content,
analytics, advertising and social medial plug-ins, that may use your data.
CHANGING OR UPDATING YOUR INFORMATION
If you have an account with us, you can manage your account at our “My Account” page, where
you may review and update your account information and access your transaction history. You
can logon to the “My Account” page anytime to ensure your account information is accurate and
up to date. To gain access to your account, you will be asked to enter your password by
following the instructions on the page. If you do not remember your password, you can reset
your password. If you need further assistance, please contact Customer Service at 707-575-
7500 or allaccess@pressdemocrat.com.
DATA SECURITY
To prevent unauthorized access, maintain data accuracy and ensure the appropriate use of
information, we have put in place physical, electronic and managerial procedures to protect the
information we collect online. While we take measures to safeguard your information, we
cannot guarantee that the security of our databases or that the information you supply will not
be intercepted while in transit over the Internet.
OTHER INFORMATION
Children's Privacy: We do not knowingly collect or store any personal information about
children under the age of 13, unless permitted by law. If we learn that a child under the age of
13 has provided us with personal information, we will delete it in accordance with applicable law.
Your California Privacy Rights: If you are a California Resident, California Law permits you to
once a year, free of charge, request and obtain certain information regarding our disclosure, if
any, of certain categories of personal information to third parties for their direct marketing
purposes in the preceding calendar year. Please send your inquiry to: Press Democrat, Attn:
Website Services, 427 Mendocino Avenue, Santa Rosa, CA 95401, or at
info@pressdemocrat.com.
Additionally, California residents who are registered users of the Services and are under the age
of 18 are entitled, in accordance with California law, to request and obtain removal of content
and information that they themselves post on the Services. You may request such removal by
emailing us at info@pressdemocrat.com.To effectuate this request, please provide the following
information: your name, email address or your website user name, year of birth, mailing
address, and a description of the material you want removed including sufficient details to
enable us to locate the material. In the subject line please note that this is a “California
Removal Request.” Your request does not ensure the complete removal of the material on the
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

Internet, as some materials that you post may be republished by another user or third party
entity.
Users Outside of the United States: Our Company is headquartered in the United States. If
you use our Sites outside of the United States, please be aware that information you provide to
us or that we obtain through your interaction with our Sites may be collected in your country and
transferred to the United States or another country, in accordance with applicable law. By using
our Services you consent to the collection, processing and storage of information about you in
the United States.
Users in the EEA and Switzerland: If you are a resident of the EEA or Switzerland, the
following information applies with respect to personal data collected through your use of our
Services.
      Purposes of processing and legal basis for processing: We process personal data
        consistent with our disclosures in this Privacy Policy. We process personal data on the
        following legal bases: (1) with your consent; (2) as necessary to perform our agreement
        to provide Services (such as when you become a subscriber); and (3) as necessary for
        our legitimate interests in providing the Services where those interests do not override
        your fundamental rights and freedoms related to data privacy.
      Transfers: Personal data we collect may be transferred to, and stored and processed in,
        the United States or any other country in which we or our affiliates or processors
        maintain facilities. We will ensure that transfers of personal data to a third country or an
        international organization are subject to appropriate safeguards.
      Individual Rights: If you are a resident of the EEA or Switzerland, we respect your rights
        according to Chapter 3 of the EU General Data Protection Regulation. In order to verify
        your identity, we may require you to provide us with personal information prior to
        accessing any records containing information about you.
For More Information: please reach out to us at Press Democrat, 427 Mendocino Avenue, Santa
Rosa, CA 95401, or at info@pressdemocrat.com.
Questions: Inquiries regarding our privacy practices may be sent to info@pressdemocrat.com
or to our address at, 427 Mendocino Avenue, Santa Rosa, CA 95401.
                              PRESS DEMOCRAT COOKIE POLICY
The Sites rely on partners to provide many features of our sites and services using data about
your use of our Sites. Below is a list of these partners with links to more information their use of
your data and how to exercise your rights to opt-out.
                                           Site Operations
Enabling features that are necessary for providing you the services on our site, such as
identifying you as being signed in, tracking content views so that we can pay the content
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

owners, remembering your preferences, and the number of times you have been shown an
advertisement.
               Partner                               Learn more about their use of data:
 BlueConic                               https://www.blueconic.com/privacy-policy/
 Zeta Global (Boomtrain)                 https://zetaglobal.com/privacy-policy/
                                              Analytics
Allowing us to understand how our services are being used, track site performance and make
improvements.
               Partner                               Learn more about their use of data:
 Google Analytics                        https://policies.google.com/privacy
 Chartbeat                               https://chartbeat.com/privacy/
                                             Advertising
Delivering advertising, including tailored advertising based on your preferences or interests
across services and devices; and measuring the effectiveness of advertisements on our
platforms and elsewhere.
               Partner                   Learn more about their use of data, and how to Opt-
                                                              out from data use:
 Google Publisher Tag                    https://policies.google.com/privacy
                                         https://adssettings.google.com/
 DoubleClick for Publishers              https://delvedeeper.com/privacy-policy/
                                         https://adssettings.google.com/
 LiveIntent                              https://liveintent.com/privacy-policy
                                         http://d.liadm.com/opt-out
 Nativo                                  https://www.nativo.com/policies-and-guidelines
                                         https://www.nativo.com/about/adchoices/
 Undertone                               https://undertone.com/privacy/
                                         https://www.undertone.com/opt-out-tool/
 AdBlade                                 https://adblade.com/doc/privacy
                                         https://adblade.com/doc/opt-out-in
 City Spark                              https://www.cityspark.com/privacy-policy
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010

 Taboola                               https://www.taboola.com/privacy-policy | Please see
                                       Taboola’s Privacy Policy under “User Choices and
                                       Opting Out” for more information.
                                          Social Media
Enabling the sharing of content from our services through social networking and other sites, and
allow you to interact and connect with such social media sites while using our Sites and
Services.
                Partner                 Learn more about their use of data, and how to Opt-
                                                         out from data use:
 True Anthem                           http://www.trueanthem.com/privacy-policy/
4849-0353-3933v.1 0059240-000010
